<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anastasis Britannica &amp; Hibernica Great Brittain and Irelands resurrection. Or the happy turn upon his Majesties happy message and happy return. The first part upon occasion of the thanksgiving, May 24. 1660. which was for his Majesties gracious message from beyond seas to the two houses, delivered upon 2 Sam.19.14. And he bowed the heart of all the men of Judah, ... The second part upon occasion of the thanksgiving, June 28. 1660. for His Majesties safe return to His kingdomes, ... By John Bradshaw pastor of Etchingham in Sussex.</title>
            <author>Bradshaw, John, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29136</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4151B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R224001</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99834701</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99834701</idno>
            <idno type="VID">39205</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29136)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 39205)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1808:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anastasis Britannica &amp; Hibernica Great Brittain and Irelands resurrection. Or the happy turn upon his Majesties happy message and happy return. The first part upon occasion of the thanksgiving, May 24. 1660. which was for his Majesties gracious message from beyond seas to the two houses, delivered upon 2 Sam.19.14. And he bowed the heart of all the men of Judah, ... The second part upon occasion of the thanksgiving, June 28. 1660. for His Majesties safe return to His kingdomes, ... By John Bradshaw pastor of Etchingham in Sussex.</title>
                  <author>Bradshaw, John, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for John Rothwel at the Bear and Fountain in Cheapside in Goldsmiths Row,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno, 1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:39205:1"/>
            <p>ANASTASIS <hi>BRITANNICA &amp; HIBERNICA,</hi> GREAT BRITTAIN <hi>and</hi> IRELANDS Reſurrection. Or the happy Turn upon his Majeſties happy MESSAGE and happy RETURN.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>The firſt Part upon occaſion of the Thanksgiving,</hi> May 24. 1660. <hi>which was for his Majeſties gracious Meſſage from beyond Seas to the two Houſes, delivered upon</hi> 2 Sam. 19.14. And he bowed the heart of all the men of <hi>Judah,</hi> even as the heart of one man, ſo that they ſent this word to the King, <hi>Return thou, and all thy ſervants.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The ſecond Part upon occaſion of the Thanksgiving,</hi> June 28. 1660. <hi>for His Majeſties ſafe</hi> Return <hi>to His Kingdomes, delivered on</hi> Verſe 15. So the King returned, and came to <hi>Jordan,</hi> and <hi>Judah</hi> came to <hi>Gilgal</hi> to go to meet the King to conduct the King over <hi>Jordan.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN BRADSHAW</hi> Paſtor of <hi>Etchingham</hi> in <hi>Suſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Hom. ſs. Iliad. Omnis autem Rex ut de <hi>Theodoſio Chryſoſtomus</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Iſa. 47.9.</hi>
                  </bibl> But theſe two things ſhall come to thee in one day, loſs of Children and Widdowhood, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Rex enim reipublicae est quaſi maritus, &amp; reſpublica de mortuo est quaſi vidua.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>A Lapid. in loc. e Cyrillo.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Rothwel</hi> at the <hi>Bear</hi> and <hi>Fountain</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide</hi> in <hi>Goldſmiths Row,</hi> Anno, 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:39205:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39205:2"/>
            <p>VIRO VERE ΕΝΔΟΞΟΤΑ'ΤΩ DOMINO <hi>GEORGIO STRODE</hi> EQUITI AURATO, JUSTITIAE PIETATISQUE CULTORI AS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIDUO, FILIO ECCLESIAE GENUINO, PRUDENTI FELICIQUE LIBERORUM PARENTI, DIGNITATIS REGIAE, EC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CLESIAE ORTHODOXAE, PATRIAE TAM FELICITATIS QUAM INCOLUMITATIS ASSERTORI STRENUO FORTIQUE PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PUGNATORI, QUI FIDELITATIS REGI DEBITAE ET FORTITUDINIS CICATRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CES IMPRESSAS ETIAMDUM GERIT, US<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>QUE AD ARAS GESTURUS, PATRONO SUO BENIGNO ET BENEFICO SAECULI EXEUNTIS FERREI ET RENASCENTIS AUREI GAUDIUM CONGRATULATUR, BONORUM OMNIUM SUMMITATEM IN SUMMO BONO COMPRECATUR, CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CIONESQUE HAS EUCHARISTICAS, <hi>I. B.</hi> CLERICUS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>D.D.D.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:39205:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39205:3"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE <hi>TO THE</hi> Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood <hi>Reader,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pilati ille Simia &amp; Antichriſti aemulu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, qui ſe non ita pridem exaltavit ſupra num'n terre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre, a ſubditis ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s non judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candum, ſed ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norandum. Quis enim judex re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſi qui rex regum.</note> I ſhall requeſt thee, if a ſtranger to me, not to ſtumble at my name. Truth it is, I have never written my name but with ſome degree of ſadneſs, ever ſince <hi>One,</hi> that bore the ſame, but none of my kindred, nor of my Principles, hath caſt a ſad blur upon it. But this is ſome
<pb facs="tcp:39205:4"/>comfort, that though one <hi>Judas</hi> was a <hi>Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> yet the other <hi>Judas,</hi> who was not <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cariot,</hi> was a loyal Diſciple. <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the <hi>Sicilian</hi> Tyrant, was odious to poſterity for his brutiſh Cruelty; yet was not the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick of another <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> the leſs rational, nor the Areopagite, <hi>Pauls</hi> hearer and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert leſs Chriſtians; nor another <hi>Diony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Corinth,</hi> ſo eminent for <hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>Holineſs,</hi> the leſs accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or the more ſuſpitious, becauſe a <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onyſius.</hi> Good carriage and honeſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples perfume and ſeaſon <hi>bad names:</hi> but <hi>bad names</hi> cannot canker <hi>good Manners.</hi> We may, and must help our <hi>ill Manners,</hi> but we cannot help our <hi>ill names;</hi> the Sir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name deſcending by <hi>birth</hi> of the <hi>fleſh,</hi> and the <hi>Chriſten</hi> name by <hi>birth</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and both before we know any thing of either. And if one perſon amongſt <hi>500.</hi> that are <hi>Cognomines,</hi> ſhall be guilty of ſome odious or audacious <hi>Crime,</hi> if any will argue for guilt upon all for his ſake, he makes himſelf guilty of a Sophiſm in <hi>Voce,</hi> called <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monymia.</hi> Nor ſhall I grant mine to be
<pb facs="tcp:39205:4"/>bad, but only abuſed by one that had a ſhare in it, but then he abuſed but his own ſhare, and not mine. <hi>Oſporco</hi> the <hi>Roman,</hi> when he was made <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſuppoſing his name to be ſomewhat homely, cauſed himſelf to be called <hi>Sergius,</hi> from which time (as a <hi>Writer</hi> ſayes) the <hi>Popes</hi> ſtill changed their names at their entrance into the Sea. I would many years ſince have changed mine, not ſo much for the <hi>ſound,</hi> but the reaſon aforeſaid, only three things letted. <hi>1.</hi> The <hi>danger</hi> I might have incurred in the late times. <hi>2.</hi> The cenſorious temper of too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, who would have voiced it a meer hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour. <hi>3.</hi> I find that anciently, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in holy Writ, names were changed, not by the parties themſelves, but by others; and thoſe either Angels or Kings. Thus <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and <hi>Sarah,</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> were alterations, at leaſt additions by Angels. This alſo ſeemed uſuall with the <hi>Chaldean Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs, 2 Kin. 24.17.</hi> Or ſuch as were great under them, <hi>Daniel 1.7.</hi> Thus did <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> call <hi>Joſeph, Zaphneth Paaneah</hi> Gen. <hi>41.45.</hi> And
<pb facs="tcp:39205:5"/>now before I take my leave, I ſhall declare in as few words as I can, what reaſons there were that ſwayed me to the Kings ſide, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the earneſt perſwaſions, and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate ſolicitations of many men, who deſerved well of me, and ſome of them generally well-beloved in the Countrey, contrary afterwards to all hopes of <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Safety,</hi> much more of advantage or advancement. And beſides thoſe obvious arguments, which are in every mans way (if they will but open their eyes to ſee them) drawn from Scripture-Precepts, both of the old and new Teſtament. The Example of the beſt men in Scripture hiſtories adhering to their <hi>Kings,</hi> and the worſt making a <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection</hi> from them; <hi>Davids</hi> tenderneſs of touching <hi>Saul,</hi> though appointed of God for his <hi>immediate Succeſſor;</hi> the expreſs and known Lawes, and Statutes of our Realm, which require all <hi>Loyalty, Duty</hi> and <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience?</hi> The <hi>Oathes</hi> of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> and I think of <hi>Supremacy</hi> alſo taken by me twice, if not <hi>thrice</hi> in one <hi>Univerſity,</hi> and as often again in the <hi>other,</hi> and <hi>twice</hi> at leaſt beſides upon other <hi>Occaſions,</hi> beſides all theſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious,
<pb facs="tcp:39205:5"/>and more general inducements, there were four more, which did exceedingly prevail with me. <hi>1.</hi> The Kings <hi>Moderation, Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Clemency, Candor, and Earneſt</hi> thirſt after <hi>Peace,</hi> and his deſire to give ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, even in things very hard and unreaſonable to be defired of him, appearing in his <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrances</hi> and <hi>Anſwers. 2.</hi> The <hi>Power</hi> of the <hi>ſword</hi> being by their ſeeming <hi>humble petitioning</hi> for it of him therein granted to be his, <hi>I thought it worthy of a worſe name than violence</hi> by force to wring it out of his <hi>hand. 3.</hi> Whereas I had learn'd from my <hi>Parents, Teachers,</hi> and ſuch as were <hi>anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,</hi> when I was <hi>young,</hi> that it was a <hi>foul Blur</hi> to any <hi>Family</hi> to be <hi>falſe</hi> to the <hi>Crown. (the expreſſion then much uſed)</hi> I after alſo found it was a main <hi>Argument Proteſtants had againſt</hi> the <hi>Jeſuited Romaniſts, viz. Seditious Practices againſt Princes.</hi> And whereas that <hi>Argument</hi> ſeemed in this caſe to be <hi>null,</hi> becauſe it was obſerved, that the moſt <hi>powerfull Preachers,</hi> the most <hi>zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Profeſſors,</hi> the moſt <hi>exact Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers,</hi> did adhere to the contrary <hi>Part,</hi> and that
<pb facs="tcp:39205:6"/>many perſons ſlack in Religion, and looſe in manners did ſide with the King; To this I ſtill anſwered: <hi>1.</hi> That the King had many tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly godly with him, that did not ſhew ſo to all, and the other party, many ſeemingly godly, which yet were not ſo. <hi>2.</hi> That the King had alſo a conſiderable number of Profeſſors and Well-wiſhers to a thorough Reformation, and the contrary party a conſiderable number of lewd debauched men, void of Religion. <hi>3.</hi> That of thoſe many which ſeemed religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and friends of Reformation, there were two ſorts, ſome that diſcovered themſelves to be perſons, either far gone, or falling into Schiſm, and theſe were to me no ſtumbling block at all, becauſe their way is not the way of Chriſt: For I know ſuch as made no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of making a breach in the Church, would make no bones to make a breach in the State, and that having rebelled againſt Chriſt in that great Law of love, they would probab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not regard the Law of Allegiance to their King, would afterwards, did in the face of the Sun. But for the other ſort of godly men and Well-willers to true Religion, I look'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:39205:6"/>them, many of them, as men meerly galled and ſurprized, verily believing, that as they did abhor ſeparation from the ordinances, ſo they never deſired, but did abhor the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the <hi>King,</hi> and his family, only they went on in the War at firſt upon the old ſcore of bringing the King to his Parliament, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and yet taking up of Arms againſt the King upon any occaſion, is flatly againſt the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and the old printed Proteſtation of Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts, that lived in the dayes of <hi>Queen Elizabeth,</hi> and King <hi>James</hi> of bleſſed Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, who were abſolutely againſt any taking up Arms against the King; and ſure ſuch as lately have done ſo, cannot tell how to open their mouths againſt thoſe men. But I muſt not make the Porch too large for the houſe. My aim in ſhort, is, (though a weak and unworthy inſtrument) to do my duty as former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in ſuffering, ſo now by acting within mine own Sphere towards the ſervice of the King, the Peace of the Kingdom, the honour of the Church, and the glory of God. To whom be glory for ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine more than his own,</hi> J. B.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>July 17. 1660.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:39205:7"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:39205:7"/>
            <head>AT THE THANKSGIVING. <hi>MAY</hi> 24. 1660.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 SAM. 19.14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And he bowed the heart of all the men of <hi>Judah,</hi> even as the heart of one man, ſo that they ſent this word to the King, <hi>Return thou and all thy ſervants.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His day is a day of Thanksgiving, and ſuch a day as deſerves a day of Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, that after ſo many improper counterfeit dayes, in which every ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, juſt and intelligent heart had more cauſe to make them dayes of mourning, we have now a true real and royal day of praiſe: the very thought of them and mention is enough to ſmut this true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing day. And yet as Phyſicians make uſe of poyſons to cure diſtempers, and Jewellers Foils to ſet off Diamonds, and Limners Shadows to ſet off beauty, ſo perhaps thoſe dayes will ſerve to illuſtrate this day. Thoſe dayes were often kept for the diſhonour that was done the King and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:39205:8"/>his true friends, and for the proſperity of his enemies; this day is kept moſt for the King, and for all true Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots, and for Parliaments in a right true conſtitution. Thoſe dayes were kept in the behalf of violent uſurpation; this in the behalf of juſt legal poſſeſſion: Thoſe dayes were kept in the behalf of ſomething ſoaring alo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> upon <hi>Iod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> his wings of divine ſucceſs by divine permiſſion; this day is kept in the behalf of true ſubjection and loyalty, ſoaring upon the Eagles wings of Law and Religion. Thoſe days were kept upon the ſhedding of blood; the blood of men, and ſo ours from the firſt <hi>Adam;</hi> the blood of Chriſtians, and ſo ours again from the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> the blood of our own Countrey-men, and ſo ours by humane aſſociation; the blood of conſciencious and loyal Patriots, and ſo ours by Sympathy and true affection: This day is kept, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves annually for ever to be kept for reſtoring the King to his own, and their people to their own in reſtoring him, and all this without one drop of blood. This <hi>Victoria in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruenta,</hi> bloodleſs victory, bringing more honour to the King, than all the bloody victories ever brought to others. Thoſe dayes were by armed violence, upon pain of a fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ruine obtruded, enforced on us; this day is willingly, nay cheerfully, nay thankfully embraced by us, and we heartily thank God this day for this Thanksgiving day. And to conclude this Preface, and not to ſtand too long at the door; when we kept thoſe, our hearts and conſciences forced us to balk the particularities, only to give thanks for general Mercies, becauſe finding the way laid out for us too foul and impoſſible, we made bold to leap over into the open Common; but the particularities and ſpecialities of this, are ſuch, as if we ſhould go out of the rode, we ſhould deſerve to be ſued by the whole Nation upon an action of high Treſpaſs. O the unſpeakable goodneſs of God to an ungrateful, ſtiff-necked, ſelf-willed, proud, divided, back-ſliding people! Ungrateful, as deſpiſers of bounty; Stiff-necked, as deſpiſers of Inſtruction; Proud, as Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temners of lawfull Authority; Divided, as Contemners of Peace, Unity and Charity. After all our Thanksgiving
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:39205:8"/>dayes, by which God hath been rather provoked than ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured; in which God hath been rather mockt, than praiſed, as ſome did manage them. God hath given us a day indeed; which to ſtumble at, would not be tenderneſs, but rather guilt of conſcience; and this Text I have read to you, ſets before you in Text-Capital Letters, the true matter and occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this Feſtival; and I deſire my heart may indite a good matter, whilſt I ſpeak of this matter; and ſpeak of things touching the King, and that my tongue may be as the Pen of a ready Writer.</p>
            <p>This verſe in the <hi>Buxtorf Hebrew</hi> Bible is the fifteenth, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>He,</hi> that is, <hi>David,</hi> &amp;c. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> The King by his gracious meſſage, by Letter or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, <hi>bowed,</hi> that is, ſo wrought upon the hearts of the men of <hi>Judah,</hi> that all of them, probably the Elders or Repreſentatives, every one, <hi>Nemine contradicente:</hi> As one man, no man diſſenting. Sent to the King, over the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the flood <hi>Jordan; Return thou;</hi> we humbly ſubmit to thy Kingly power, we are your Majeſties loyal Subjects, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn back to your Kingly office, and all thy ſervants; we exempt none, every one with thee is welcome for thy ſake. Come with all thy Retinue, and with all the honour that poſſibly can be.</p>
            <p>How clear and full is the Parable betwixt the hiſtory of the Text, and the Hiſtory of the day! as if theſe things mentioned in the Text, had been in ſome ſort Types or Shadowes (which yet they were not) of thoſe things we ſee this day.</p>
            <p>Yea, here is every thing in the Text that we rejoyce for in the day. We rejoyce in a King, and here is a King in the Text; <hi>He,</hi> that is, King <hi>David;</hi> We rejoyce in the Kings prevalency, and here is <hi>Davids</hi> prevalency, he bowed or inclined: we rejoyce in ſuch a prevalency as is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out compulſion, without force or blood, and ſo it is here, <hi>He bowed the hearts.</hi> We rejoyce in the Subjects hearty ſubjection, and in the peoples hearts to their King; and here is the peoples hearts, <hi>He bowed the hearts of the men
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:39205:9"/>of Judah.</hi> We rejoyce to ſee Allegiance and Loyalty bound cloſe together in Unity, and here you read, <hi>He bowed their hearts as one mans.</hi> We rejoyce that after ſo long a diſtance there is now an intercourſe; here is the ſame, they ſent to the King; We rejoyce that there is not only an intercourſe, but a fair correſpondency, nor that only, but an humble and hearty invitation, a clear and full reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a ready and cheerfull ſubjection and ſubmiſſion, <hi>Return thou and all thy ſervants with thee,</hi> ſo it is here.</p>
            <p>So that I cannot divide my Text, but I muſt alſo diſſect the day. The diſtribution of the firſt muſt needs be the deſcription of the ſecond.</p>
            <p>To me there ſeems in both a fourfold complication of a wonder and a bleſſing, of ſomething very ſtrange, and ſomething very good.</p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Miſi &amp; vici</hi> as ſtrange as <hi>vidi &amp; vici.</hi>
               </note> Here is a bare meſſage conquering: a bleſſed kind of Conqueſt, and a ſtrange kind of Conqueſt; there is the complication of both together in the happy and ſtrange operation of the Kings Meſſage or Letter.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Complication of wonder and goodneſs is in the hearts bowed: the hearts of all men are by nature ſtiff, ſince the fall: The Jewes are eſpecially noted for hardneſs of heart, and after Apoſtacy from God, or Defections from a King, mens hearts are ſtill harder, yet the mens hearts were bowed, yea the men of <hi>Judahs</hi> hearts, yea, after de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections from <hi>David.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third ſtrange, but happy fold or complication is of diverſity and unity; the men of <hi>Judah</hi> were ſeveral and many, and yet their heart was one, their principles, their apprehenſions, and no doubt their affections were divers, and perhaps contrary, but now on a ſuddain upon this meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, though perhaps ſome might come with claſhing thoughts, all are bowed, all reſolved one way.</p>
            <p>The fourth Complication is of an humble invitation after a ſtubborn defection, and ſometime a ſeeming impoſſible re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation, <hi>Return thou and all thy,</hi> &amp;c. I may make but two general parts.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:39205:9"/> 1. THe peoples converſion to their King, <hi>and he bowed,</hi> &amp;c. 2. The Kings reverſion to his people, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn thou,</hi> &amp;c. Both theſe are ſet out by the cauſe: of the converſion, the cauſe is the Kings Meſſage to the people; the cauſe of the reverſion is the peoples meſſage to the King. And here firſt we ſee how like the Kings Method in converting his Subjects, is to Gods in convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſinners.</p>
            <p>I ſpeak here of a reſemblance only, and that at a great diſtance. For Creatures reſemble not God to uſe the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of <hi>Petrus de Aliaco in eſſendo &amp; in perfectione quid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditativa,</hi> but <hi>in repraeſentando &amp; ratione repraeſentativa;</hi> or as <hi>Bonaventure</hi> diſtinguiſhes, it is not <hi>ſimilitudo aequiparantiae,</hi> but <hi>imitationis.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. de Gratia, &amp; lib. arbit. c. 7.</note> As therefore in divine grace <hi>Auſtin</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſheth betwixt operating and co-operating grace: <hi>Deus</hi> ſaith he, <hi>co-operando perficit quod operando incipit.</hi> And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt preventing and ſubſequent Grace, <hi>Dei</hi> (ſaith the ſame Father) <hi>gratia nolentem praevenit ut velit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Enchir. c. 32.</note> 
               <hi>volentem ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequitur ne fruſtra velit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Proſp. epugr. 45.</note> And as there is a diſtinction of <hi>gratia ducens &amp; concomitans, gratia excitans &amp; adjuvans,</hi> which makes <hi>Ber.</hi> ſay, <hi>Conatus noſtri &amp; caſſi ſunt ſi non adjuventur, &amp; nulli ſi non excitentur.</hi> In like manner we may ſay,
<note place="margin">De gratia &amp; li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> arbit.</note> but in a lower ſphere, King <hi>David</hi> by his preventing, leading, exciting, ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating grace (for we do aſcribe to Kings Grace and favour) doth begin the work of political converſion and reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation. He ſtrikes the firſt ſtroke towards the faſtning the King and people together. Yet not working as God doth by any ſupernatural power over the will, by any inward infuſions, but extrinſically as man works upon man by mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral perſwaſion. Only as Kings are called Gods becauſe they are like God in Supremacy, as higher than others; in power, as ſtronger than others; Gods in honour, as more noble than others; ſo herein they are like God, who loves us before we love him, and woes us before we ſeek to him,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.17.</note> giving before we ask, yielding to us before we ſeek to him. Thus doth
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:39205:10"/>King <hi>David</hi> in the Text; he firſt ſends to them, before they ſend to him, and woes them to ſend to him, before they ſend to him to come to them. He is not only firſt in dignity, but firſt in benignity: His is not only prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency in Honour, but precedency in kindneſs. And what King <hi>David</hi> doth in the Text, King <hi>Charles</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond doth in the day. The firſt open and viſible ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is his. He prevents his Subjects with gracious tenders of Peace and Love. He knows that <hi>Amor</hi> is <hi>magnum ſatellitium,</hi> and that <hi>timeri oportet Caeſarem, ſed plus diligi.</hi> He that ſaid <hi>Agree with thy enemy quickly in the gate,</hi> hath taught his Majeſty to begin timouſly the work of pacification, and to be firſt at the gate for entrance before others could be ready to open them. And as he imitates God the Father in an antecedent love, ſo God the Son in an antecedent Call. He ſtands at the door, and knocks. He muſt needs be a very Sot, or an envious man that will not ſay, that the Kings Wiſdome, Favour and Goodneſs is much to be honoured, therefore let his Majeſty have his due honour, but accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his religious and ſelf-denying deſires, let God be chiefly magnified in all this. A magnetical touch from him is the firſt and principal cauſe of the King and the Parliaments mutual and ſweet attractions of, and tenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy towards one another. It is the God of love and peace that hath made love and peace to abound betwixt King and Subjects. It is the Lords doing, and is marvelous in our eyes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abigail</hi> was a very prudent woman, and to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended highly for her prudence; and <hi>David</hi> wanted not for language to do it, yet he choſe to aſcribe all prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally to God. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.32. <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord God of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, which hath ſent thee this day to meet me.</hi> God by an occult hand and a ſtill voice ſends us upon many errands, and we perceive it not. What is certainly true of all men, is moſt ſignally and emphatically true of Kings. <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.1. The Kings heart is in the hand of the Lord, as the rivers of waters, he turneth it whither ſoever he will. God hath a ſpecial hand on the heart of a King, as he hath a ſpecial
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:39205:10"/>hand in the erecting a King, and a ſpecial hand in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a King, which is not done by the multitude of an hoſt, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 33.16. and therefore by the Lord of hoſtes, ſo alſo in guiding of a King. He turns it as the rivers of waters; that is, he draws a Channel for it. So that it ſhall go ſuch a way, and yet go by its own natural inclination too. A ſimilitude, which to my thoughts, doth to the life ſet out to us Gods Providence, and over-ruling hand con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring with the freedome of our Wills, and activity of our minds and ſpirits, For the waters runs in a declining trench, the weight and the fluid humidity carries it on, but a previous hand prepares the trench. So here.</p>
            <p>Well, Bleſſed be that immortal and wiſe Engineer in heaven that thus guided the Kings heart to bow his Subjects hearts; and next, Bleſſed be the Kings prudence and innate goodneſs, who hath ſaved the ſhedding of ſo much Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian blood, as elſe had been ſhed, had it not thus been prevented. And let us imitate theſe two Princes in their imitation: Let us ſtrive to be firſt in offices of love, mercy and peace. The feet of ſome of the Kings enemies were ſwift to ſhed blood, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.16. Their feet did run to evil, and did make haſte to ſhed blood. The King that doth truly <hi>patrizare</hi> for his royal Father, did not deſire warre or blood-ſhed, but was the moſt earneſt ſuiter for peace to his own Subjects that ever was. I ſay the King, his feet are ſwift to ſave ſhedding of blood. Let us learn to be ſwift to ſave and deliver our Neighbours and brethren; let us be quick to offices of Juſtice, and offices of mercy. Let our feet to do good be as Hynds feet, <hi>Hab.</hi> 3.19. We often read in Scripture of a <hi>Nunc ergo; Now therefore,</hi> that is now preſently, ſpeedily, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.7. <hi>Nunc ergo arripite,</hi> as the vulgar Latin. <hi>Venite, Gen.</hi> 11.3. <hi>Faciamus lateres,</hi> go to, let us make brick. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 95. <hi>Oh come let us wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. Beda</hi> renders it <hi>Feſtinate.</hi> See what haſte <hi>Abraham</hi> made in the way and work of hoſpitality. <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. v. 6. <hi>Abraham</hi> haſted to the Tent to <hi>Sarah,</hi> there was haſte expreſſed in his motion: make ready quickly three meaſures of meales, there was haſte in his command. And again <hi>Abraham</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:39205:11"/>runnes to the heard, there was haſte in expedition, and the yong man haſted to dreſſe it: there was haſte in the preparation. And <hi>David</hi> ſends word to the men of <hi>Judah,</hi> why are ye the laſt to bring back the King to his houſe? <hi>Pudeat eſſe postremos,</hi> let us not be laſt in offices of piety, offices of mercy, of hoſpitality, much leſſe in of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of duty, fidelity, allegiance, loyalty. In theſe let us both take and give example.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>PART 1.</head>
               <p>WE come now to the firſt Complication of a wonder and a bleſſing, and that is, a victorious meſſage ſent from King <hi>David</hi> to his ſubjects the men of <hi>Judah.</hi> A meſſage full of grace, as taking no notice of their defecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from him. A meſſage full of love and compliance, as ſeeking re-union and reconciliation with them. There were eight ingredients that made this overture ſo ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It was but a meſſage, it was not an army to invade and to inforce; and yet ſure <hi>David</hi> that was ſo beloved of God, that his very name ſignifyed beloved, could not be ſo ill beloved of men, but he might either for love, or money, or both have obtained a ſufficient force amongſt the <hi>Gileadites,</hi> yea perhaps amongſt the <hi>Ammonites.</hi> He that was not only more ſafely but more kindly entertaind on the other ſide of the water, amongſt ſtrangers of another tribe: He that had ſuch gifts and preſents ſent him, for the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtenance of himſelf and his people with him, could not he have obtained an armed power? But he makes uſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of words than of ſwords, and to ſend out his declaration than to ſhoot out his arrowes, or make proviſion of Ammunition. He chooſeth rather <hi>dul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ia verba</hi> than <hi>dura verbera.</hi> And this was one ingredient, which puts me in mind of that ſpeech of <hi>Euripides</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſick minds, whether ſick of greif, or anger, or hate, or feare, are often cured by words. Sure he that brought this meſſage was a good man, and came with good tidings,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:39205:11"/>and deſerved of the men of <hi>Judah</hi> a good reward.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As it was no worſe than a meſſage, ſo it was a gracious meſſage, not thundring out revenge and deſtruction; He might have ſent a meſſage of terrour, and he that brought it might have been the meſſenger of death, and have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred the <hi>Sanedrim</hi> with his cloaths rent, as 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.2. The <hi>Amalekite</hi> came to <hi>David.</hi> But it was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, good tidings.</p>
               <p>It was not like <hi>Rehoboam</hi>'s harſh anſwer, my litle finger ſhall be thicker than my fathers loyns, and I will make your yoake heavier, and I have rods in brine for you, I will whip you with ſnakes or ſcorpions, every ſtripe ſhall be a ſting too. He conſidered not, that to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſo thick and heavy was the way, not only to be quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of breath, both he and his family, but to catch a fall; He ſhould rather have hearkned to gray then green heads, who could have told him, that <hi>acerbitas imperii brevitate ſaepe compenſatur.</hi> But <hi>David</hi> was much wiſer in his meſſage than <hi>Rehoboam</hi> in his anſwer: For the returne to his meſſage was <hi>[Returne thou and all &amp;c.]</hi> the returne to <hi>Rehoboam</hi>'s was quite contrary, but no way juſtifiable, <hi>what portion have we in David? to your tents, O Iſrael;</hi> an undutifull anſwer beſpeaking an ungodly and unrighteous rebellion.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It was not only a gracious meſſage, as free from indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, but alſo a loving meſſage, as free from conteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſcarce an expoſtulation, but ſuch a one as covers kindeneſs. <hi>q. d.</hi> I hope you will not be the laſt in loyalty that are firſt in Conſanguinity.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It was a meſſage from a King, not from a fellow-ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and who knows not that majeſty carries efficacy? For where the word of a King is, there is power. The words of him that is the annointed muſt needs, like oile, ſinke into the hearts of the people, if they be not harder than an adamant. Yea if hard, yet it prevails, <hi>Eraſmus</hi> ſayes a Kings word is like lightning, it melts not wax, but melts and diſſolves the ſteele.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Their own King, their own leige Lord, not a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigner, though in a forraign country; not a ſtranger, though
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:39205:12"/>exiled from his own home. Thus is He <hi>pater patriae,</hi> and ſhall not the words of a Father prevaile? Thus is he a terreſtrial God <hi>(I have ſaid ye are gods)</hi> and ſhall not his word as well carry a ſemblable efficacy, as well as his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon carry a ſemblable majeſty?</p>
               <p n="6">6. Their innocent and blameleſs King, of whom it might have been ſaid, as it was after of his Antitype, but not ſo infallibly and abſolutely, <hi>Why? What evil hath he done?</hi> what colour had <hi>Abſalom</hi> for the ſnatching the ſword by violence out of the hand of <hi>David?</hi> If the <hi>Militia</hi> was truly <hi>Davids,</hi> why doth <hi>Abſalm</hi> by violence and fraud wreſt and wring it from him? And if it was <hi>Abſaloms,</hi> how then was <hi>David</hi> King, except he voluntarily quitted his power, and left himſelf only a naked Title.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Their afflicted King; the Meſſage of an innocent Prince muſt needs carry a great ſtroke, but much more if under affliction. We often read of the beſt Princes that they have been ſome part of their reign, either in the beginning, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the end thereof much afflicted. And beſides Princes, many other renowned perſons, <hi>Coſmo de Medicis,</hi> who next after his father <hi>Johannes,</hi> was the foundation of a great and renowned family, was the moſt honourable and famous Common-wealths man that ever had been in any memory before his time for Authority, Wiſdome, Juſtice, Riches, Liberality and Magnificence; the firſt part of his life was full of troubles, he was exiled and frequently in danger of death, but after lived and governed moſt happily: He was happy in his ſon <hi>Petrus de Medicis,</hi> and in his Grand-child <hi>Laurentius de Medicis:</hi> And I hope a branch of that family will flouriſh for ever. The greater the perſon, the greater the affliction, and the greater that is, the more ſhould their words move affection.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Their injured King, injured by <hi>Abſalom</hi> his natural ſon; injured by the men of <hi>Judah,</hi> his Political ſons; injured by his chief Councellour, <hi>Achitophel;</hi> baſely uſed by <hi>Shimei;</hi> yea injured after many acts of Grace and favour, after great deliverances wrought for the people: <hi>Ver.</hi> 9. <hi>And all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were at ſtrife throughout all the Tribes of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>ſaying,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:39205:12"/>the King ſaved us out of the hand of our enemies, and he deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vored us out of the hand of the</hi> Philiſtins, <hi>and now he is fled out of the land for</hi> Abſalom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe eight ingredients mixt together in the Kings meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, the body of the people being before well prepared by conſideration, wrought very effectually to the removing of any <hi>Scirrhus</hi> from the hearts of the men of <hi>Judah,</hi> and to make them ſo ſoft and tender, as to bow and yield to this healing touch of the Kings hand in his meſſage.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Application.</hi> And have I not all this while been ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of things pertaining to our King and Countrey? I ſhall only crave this clemency of you, that whilſt I make up the parallel, which I ſhall do as briefly as I can: you would not either imagine that I diſparage you, as if your minds were ſo dull, as that you had not done it already, or that I flatter the King, in whoſe preſence, as I do not now ſpeak, ſo neither do I ſpeak beſides Truth, or beyond ſobriety; nor would I have you to imagine, that I detract from, or neglect in my ſpeech the Worthies aſſembled in this moſt honourable, free and happy Parliament, which ſhall be as fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous to poſterity for this wiſe, juſt, pious, loyal work of inviting home the King with ſo much love and duty, as the <hi>Bran</hi> of another Parliament hath been, and will be to all ages infamous for deſtroying the gracious Father, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſing the hopefull Son. I call them <hi>Bran,</hi> becauſe they had been often ſifted, and the worſt was ſtill left in the ſive. I pray you alſo let us bleſs God, as we go along, for that it is the work of the day, as the parallel is work for the day: <hi>Verbum ſapientibus,</hi> a little to the intelligent is enough.</p>
               <p>And bleſſed be God for the Kings Meſſage, that it was no worſe than a Meſſage. Had the Kings heart been ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on revenge, he would have ſent in another ſtrein. Let us not flatter our ſelves, or undervalew this favour. The peace of thoſe two great Nations full South of us, might have begotten War againſt us; nor would the Sword-men of two ſuch rich and populous Nations have been willing to receive a <hi>Quietus eſt,</hi> or to ſit down as Reformadoes, when ſo juſt a cauſe, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:39205:13"/>ſuch good booties, and ſo well beloved a pay-maſter had given incouragement,</p>
               <p n="2">2. A gracious meſſage, Bleſſed be our gracious God, and bleſſed of God be our gracious King. For he declares he neither deſires the blood, nor dammage of his people: that he is ready to pardon, nay, to remove the reproaches of them that have been reproachers.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Which ſufficiently makes good the third thing, that it is meſſage of love and comfort, declaring a readineſs, not only to pardon, but to beſtow, not only to forgive, but to give.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It was a Kings meſſage, and whatever of late years hath been acted or ſpoken in a tendency to eclipſe the dignity of that high office, yet the Scriptures, the Lawes and cuſtomes of all Nations have ever been to honour it with the higheſt degree of humane honour. To ſpeak of regall dignity deſerves a day and a Text by it ſelf. This is enough to ſhew why this meſſage ſhould be ſo ſoveraign in operation, they are next to God, and I will only men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that of <hi>Tertullian: Reges in ſolius Dei potestate ſunt: a quo ſunt ſecundi, post quem Primi, ante omnes &amp; ſuper omnes Deos &amp; homines.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Our own Kings meſſage, True indeed; driven out by meanes of a ſubtile, traiterous <hi>Abſalom,</hi> a politicall ſon, yet a politick rebell, and ſo forced to be as a ſtranger to his own people, and to go over Jordan for ſuccour and ſafety.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Our blameleſſe King, and yet (to take in the two laſt) our afflicted injured King. I would ſpeake much upon this part, and my heart would indite with more life and affection then yet it hath done: and oh that I had leave from his Majeſty to limb out his and His Fathers ſufferings. But his very goodneſſe ſeems to take me off, who in his letter to the noble Generall wiſhes that the memory of what is paſſed may be buried in the world, and who heartily ſeeks the reconciliation of all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:39205:13"/>
               <head>PART II.</head>
               <p>I Therefore come in a few words to the ſecond Complica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Here are hearts bowed, and the hearts of ſuch as had been, if not active againſt <hi>David,</hi> yet not active for him, and however the hearts of the latter ſort might be and were flexible, yet no doubt the other were more ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>1</label> 
                  <hi>Obſer.</hi> That even ſtubborn hearts, when before prepared and wakened by conſideration, may at laſt be bowed. <hi>v.</hi> 9. they were ſtartled and began to conſider what they had done in ſetting up <hi>Abſalom,</hi> and now when the meſſage comes, it ſetts them right, this warme meſſage, proceeding from an heart in which was kindled love and piety, thawed their hearts, and made them begin to be more gentle.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Application.</hi>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Appli. </seg>
                  </label> And here perhaps is not ſo full or cleare a compliance betwixt the hiſtory of the Text, and the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the day. For as for the worthies of this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I look on them as ſuch, whoſe hearts before the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage were internally bowed, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> not in outward expreſſion and declarative till the meſſage came. At leaſt there were hearty good wiſhes, this I believe no man can doubt of well, this day is by their order. And bleſſed be the Lord for their choyce to that great work, and their meeting upon their choice, &amp; their good enacting upon their aſſembling, and their loyall reception of the Kings meſſage, and their dutifull and gratefull returne made to his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty: and let us keep the day joyfully, but yet inoffenſively. The King, being both a temperate and religious perſon, would have all that love him rejoyce inoffenſively and in the fear of God; and the true Chriſtian way of rejoycing is with ſome coſt upon externall expreſſions of joy, to beſtow a fit proportion upon the poor, that they may rejoyce with us, that are intereſſed with us in the ſame bleſſings.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obſerv.</hi> Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>2</label> How the injuries offered to a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:39205:14"/>gracious, loving and pious Prince by his own people, works ſtrongly upon mens hearts, when ſeriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The injuries of others cannot but ſomewhat affect us. A man would be loth to ſee a Turke wronged. Though man be fallen, and through his fall becomes injurious to men, by being firſt injurious to God, &amp; though men are often inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious themſelves, either through paſſion or covetouſneſs, yet they love not to ſee others to be injured by others, but will ordinarily either whiſper or exclaim againſt it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But Secondly offered to a perſon of quality and deſert, eſpecially to a King is very intolerable in the thoughts of men, if men. Yea ſuppoſe he were <hi>flagellum Dei,</hi> as many ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants we read of in Scripture were; yet they had honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able titles given them, to ſhew they were to be exempted from contempt, and conſequently from all other indignities and injuries: who more wicked then <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morphoſed, at leaſt degraded by a divine hand down to brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhnes, depoſed by God and none but God, not only from his throne, but his very reaſon, yet is he called more than once the <hi>ſervant of God, Jer.</hi> 25.9. <hi>Jer.</hi> 27.6. which title is given him not from his piety, but from his dignity, not from his grace, but from his office. One askes the queſtion how <hi>David</hi> in thoſe hot countries ſhould be ſo cold, when old that no cloathes could keep him warme, 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 1.1. Several rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are given by authors, as becauſe he was borne of ancient parents or loſt much bloud in the wars, but <hi>Lyranus</hi> from <hi>Rabbi Solomon</hi> ſayes it was for cutting off the skirt of <hi>Sauls</hi> garment. But we need not ſeek any farther for a reaſon, than the Scripture leads us to, which was old age; and for the other his heart ſmote him, he was troubled in conſcience for what he had done, and if <hi>David</hi> was troubled in mind for cutting off but a skirt, how would his conſcience have terrify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, if he had cut off his life.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But then thirdly who can with patience ſee injuries of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to a gracious and religious King, gracious towards men, and religious towards God? It was enough not only, to bow, but to breake the heart of the men of <hi>Judah</hi> to think that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:39205:14"/>
                  <hi>David,</hi> who had been their Deliverer, ſhould want a Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer, and he that ſaved them ſo often from flying and exile, ſhould now flee, and become an Exile, that the ſweet Singer of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhould be a ſad Mourner out of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> That he who by his ſweet touch upon the harp was able to drive away the Devil from <hi>Saul,</hi> ſhould himſelf be driven away by the devil of rebellion. It could not but peirce their hearts to think, that ſo noble a Champion as ſlew <hi>Goliah,</hi> the glory and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of the <hi>Philiſtins,</hi> and in cutting off his head, did quite cut in pieces, or break their body, ſhould being the head, be divided from the body of his people by an <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalom,</hi> the ſword indeed of Gods wrath againſt him and them. That he that was ſo good natured, as to bewail the death of <hi>Saul,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.12. his implacable adverſary, and the death of <hi>Abſalom</hi> his traiterous ſon ſhould not be ſooner thought on, nor find ſo much good nature amongſt his own people, as to be ſooner ſought to for a return, yea, yet more, ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, as he was, even one of the moſt excellent and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous inſtruments of God, in penning a part of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. In ſo much, that along in the Title of his Pſalms it is <hi>Miſmor le David,</hi> a Pſalm to <hi>David,</hi> ſo the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ordinarily and primarily is uſed, &amp; the LXX. ſtill render it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. To ſhew they were not Pſalmes of <hi>David tanquam aucloris,</hi> but <hi>tanquam Scriptoris,</hi> and that they were dictated to him by the Holy Ghoſt. That a man ſo acquainted with God, that he was one of the moſt ſpecial Receptacles of the ſpirits in-breathing, ſhould not find a Receptacle to breath in with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his own territories.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Application.</hi> I can think no other, but that the ſufferings of <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt of glorious memory, and the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, our preſent muniment and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament next under God and Chriſt, have made a deep im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion upon the hearts of all that are men. But let us ſtill acknowledge to the glory of our good God, that as the bowing of hearts is the impreſsion, and both his Majeſties and his royal Fathers ſufferings are the ſeal, ſo the divine hand is that chiefly which hath both ſet to, and ſo ſet
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:39205:15"/>home the ſeal, that the impreſſion is made ſo deep upon all mens hearts. And ſeeing it is ſo, that the
<note n="*" place="margin">I call him the greateſt of Martyrs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe others ſuffer only in defence of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, he in defence both of Religion and moral Juſtice, and humane ſociety.</note> greateſt of Martyrs, the firſt that ever reigned over us of that name, is not only out of the reach of his enemies malice, but out of the reach of his friends gratitude, who can as little now do any thing for him, as the other can do againſt him. The Lord give to all men that ſpirit of ingenuity, that beſides what al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance and love they pay our dear Soveraign for his own ſake, they would alſo pay that to him, which could they reach him, they would think due to his glorious Father. It being all the reaſon in the world, that he who ſo juſtly and happily inherits his Fathers Throne, ſhould alſo receive his Fathers debts owing to him.</p>
               <p>I come to the third Complication of Diverſity and Unity, <hi>Many men, and yet unanimous.</hi> They were all as one man, becauſe not one diſſented. After the bowing and melting of nearts, follows knitting and ſothering of hearts. And conſidering what way they had ſtood under, it was a wonder: conſidering what good produced, it was a Bleſſing, a Mercy. And to ſpeak but as it is, there is no ſothering without melting, nor will mens hearts be eaſily joyned in unity, that are not firſt melted by humility. As Pride is the cauſe of Contention, and Separation and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, ſo Humility is the cauſe of union and conjunction. And thus I have an opportunity to make a tranſition from the cauſe of the King to the cauſe of the Church. But I doubt whether there can be any tranſition, ſith the cauſe is the very ſame, or at leaſt ſo nearly connext that either the fall or riſe of the one, muſt be the fall or riſe of the other. Unity, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Church or State, is, in my eye, the moſt glorious and happy thing that is upon earth. This makes the Pſalmiſt cry out. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 133.1. <hi>Quam bonum &amp; jucundum!</hi> good and pleaſant. Many things are good that are not at preſent very delightſome, as faſting, weeping, mortification, ſelf-denyal, ſuffering. And many things are pleaſant which are not good, as many things pleaſing to the fleſh which pleaſe not God, but Unity is both: ſo greatly good, and ſo great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:39205:15"/>comely, that the Pſal miſt cannot expreſs it; <hi>How good!</hi> this was the praiſe of the primitive Chriſtians. <hi>Acts</hi> 4.32. <hi>The multitude were of one heart, and one mind. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munis Chriſtus, &amp; unus communis Sumptus,</hi> as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith. <hi>Origen</hi> obſerves out of 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.24. That though in an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly race all run, and only one of all obtains the prize; yet in the heavenly race, all that run, obtain: and yet theſe are in the <hi>Protaſis</hi> called One. <hi>Origen in Hom.</hi> There is none ſo fit to bear rule as they to whom God hath given both ability and faculty to make peace with a deſire to do it. <hi>Moſes</hi> that did keep rule betwixt the two <hi>Hebrews,</hi> did afterwards bear rule over the <hi>Hebrews.</hi> Bleſſed is that land like to be, whoſe King is a Peace-maker, that hath much practiſed it in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Kingdomes and States, whoſe delight is to bow mens hearts to unity. Who ſo fit to be a <hi>Moſes</hi> in <hi>Iſrael?</hi> and who ſo fit to govern the Church, as they that are true She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pherds and not wolves, and keep the flock from being ſcattered, and torn in pieces, or uſe endeavours ſo to do? There is ſo near a Tye betwixt <hi>ens &amp; unum,</hi> that when any thing looſes its unity, it hazards it entity, eſpecially then when much of the being is aggregative, and conſiſts in the cloſing of ſeverals into one. And were it ſo that Chriſtians had the true love of God in their hearts, there would be a far greater union of hearts one with another than there is. And this is that,
<note place="margin">Tit. 144.</note> that excellent Writer <hi>Raymundes de Sabunde</hi> doth clearly demonſtrate: For love (ſaith he) changes the will into that which is chiefly beloved. And if that be ſome one thing which is common to all, and beloved of all, then all thoſe loves are united in one. And ſo there would be perfect unity amongſt men, and no man would have his own will, but Gods Will. But when every man loves his own will primarily, he then ſeeks that chiefly, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes what oppoſes it. When men meet not in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon love of God, but love themſelves firſtly and chiefly, they oppoſe all that ſtand in their light, and hence come ſtrifes, and wars, and animoſities. And ſo ſayes <hi>Solomon,</hi> from Pride comes Contention. But if all mens hearts were bowed, they would ſweetly cloſe and claſp together, as trees
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:39205:16"/>bowed, meet together and make one Arbour. Oh how glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious were Chriſtianity, if the hearts of Chriſtians were as the heart of one man! If we had all, not only the ſame Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, as indeed we have in the Apoſtles Creed, as to pure Fundamentals, but the ſame Catechiſm, the ſame form of Worſhip, and Rule of Diſcipline, and all ſet free both From homely rudeneſs in one extream, and vain ſuperſtition in the other: ſure I am, it was oecumenical Unity of all perſons and all ages our Saviour prayd for to continue in his Church.</p>
               <p n="1">1. There is a fourfold Unity, ſay the Schooles: The firſt and greateſt is, that which denies all diviſibility, and ſo nothing diviſible is one. And thus the divine nature is only one</p>
               <p n="2">2. Is the Unity of compoſition, when ſeveral things are compounded together: as water and earth make one lump, ſoul and body make one man, and this may be divided and ſevered.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Unity of Aggregation; as many things meeting to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in one: ſo many grains of wheat, or any other grain makes one heap. Many people in one Houſe make one Company; in one Church, make one Congregation.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Is Unity of Conformity, and this is threefold:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Unity of Nature and <hi>Species,</hi> and ſo all individuals of the ſame <hi>Species</hi> are one. So <hi>Plato, Socrates, Peter, Paul, James, John,</hi> are all one.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Of Will, to will and wiſh the ſame things.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Of Action and operation, to joyn in the ſame work: as when many Souldiers joyn in fighting, many Labourers in reaping, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The firſt Chriſt prayed not for, which is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to be in any Creature, nor properly for the ſecond. For the third he did, that we may be, as in Heaven we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly ſhall be, one collected body. The fourth, he chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aymed at, in the two laſt branches of it, that we might will and wiſh, judge and ſpeak the ſame things. And would Chriſt pray for any thing that is not glorious and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent? What Nation is it that can ſubſiſt without this? What Army can conquer without it? This we ſhall find perfectly obſerved by the Saints Triumphant in Glory, and it ſhould be ſought by Saints Militant in the way to Glory.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:39205:16"/>
               <p> The fourth fold or complication of a wonder and a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, is their invitation, implying both ſubmiſſion and a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of reconciliation: It was ſtrange, but well they did ſo, yea, the moſt probable way of their felicity. The Kings re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn was very probably the return of their ſettlement in peace and all proſperity. This word, <hi>Return,</hi> implyes, 1. Their ſenſe of his abſence. 2. Their deſire of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. 3. The ſecurity given of his ſafety and honour up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Return. For no doubt, the moſt bloody and treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous enemies he had, deſired his preſence, not to deliver him, but to deſtroy him. So that this Meſſage, was as much as to ſay, Return and fear not, Return and welcome; yea, thou and all thy ſervants.</p>
               <p>But 1. Here is his abſence implyed, and the occaſion wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy our enquiry; What! <hi>David</hi> gone from his people? Little do wicked people conſider, and as little able are any to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, how great their folly, and how abominable their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe is, who drive and keep away a gracious, juſt and loving Prince? Is not this to quench out the light of <hi>Iſra l?</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.17. To drive the Sun out of our Horizon, and to draw upon our ſelves darkneſſe and confuſion? Ever ſince we have been without our King, we have been but in the dark, neither knowing where we are, or where to be. How have we ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled and fallen over every new Government layd before us! Is not he called the breath of our Noſtrils? <hi>Lam.</hi> 4. and what have we been all this time, ſuch eſpecially whoſe hearts are with the King, but as ſo many dead men, out ſouls being as it were ſequeſtred from our bodies, whilſt our King was driven from his Kingdomes?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Here is his preſence deſired: Return thou, we deſire to ſee you upon your Throne, and in your Preſence-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; we will ſee your Palaces, and Royal Manſions ſhall be ready prepared and furniſht for you.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Here is his ſafety and Honour provided: not onely ſafely, but honourably, chearfully, joyfully received and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com'd home again. And this is that, which when we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the ſtrength of the enemy, and the ſucceſſe of their Forces, and the continual blaſts of all undertakings for the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:39205:17"/>King, we thought, in the ſight of fleſh and blood to be impoſſible, at leaſt improbable; but when we conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Piety, Charity, Humility, Meekneſſe, Clemency, and the frequent Prayers, Teares of the late good King, and how many ungratefull injuries, baſe affronts and cruel uſages were offerd to him, we hoped then that ſo many prayers and teares would not be unheard, and ſo may injuries would not be paſt by; and the rather, becauſe his Son, our gracious King, was eſteemed of ſober intelligent men, as a Son tread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Fathers ſteps: Only here was the miſtake, in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, we thought God would cut the way of the Kings Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn by the ſword; but our gracious God hath done it in a farre more happy, glorious way, than we did imagine and could conceive. The King is ſent for, and all his ſervants, a true ſigne of their love who ſent to the King to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, that they loved his ſervants: For, if I love the King, I cannot hate, perſecute, or ſeek the deſtruction of ſuch as I believe, have been true and faithfull ſervants to him. Yea, God hath granted the King his own in his own way, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his own and his Fathers deſires: that is, with love, and without blood-ſhed. And, though I never yet was at his Majeſties Cloſet-door, nor ever ſaw his Royal Face; yet I do verily believe, and am fully perſwaded, it hath been his conſtant and ardent prayer for many yeares together, that God would reſtore him to his own again without the ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of blood, and that God would bow the hearts of his Subjects to him. And, we may now ſay with joyfull hearts, as it is, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 21.1 — 7. <hi>The King ſhall joy in thy ſtrength, O Lord, and in thy ſalvation how greatly ſhall he rejoyce! Thou hast given him his hearts deſire, and haſt not withholden the requeſts of his lips,</hi> &amp;c. Yea, it now appeares that God did file up the prayers, and bottle up the teares ſhed in <hi>Carisbrook</hi>-Caſtle, and in other places by that King of Martyrs and moſt precious of Saints, whom my tongue could hardly ever mention without teares: and who is he that will not now give thanks? Surely, an evil ſpirit from the Lord hath their hearts in Fee-ſimple, that will not be removed by the ſweet Muſick of this Day; For it may be
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:39205:17"/>ſaid of almoſt the whole body of the Nation, as it is, <hi>Eſay</hi> 9.3, 4. <hi>They joy before thee according to the joy in harveſt, and as men rejoyce when they divide the ſpoil. For thou haſt broken the yoak of his burden, and the ſtaffe of his ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, the Rod of his oppreſſour as in the day of</hi> Midian. The joy of harveſt is for what labour hath brought in, the joy of dividing the ſpoil, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for what hazard and victory hath brought in; But our joy is for a ſtrange Providence, and an incomparable bleſſing obtained without paines or hazard. A bleſſing dropt down from Heaven into our lapps and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes. And now what ſhall we render to the Lord for all his benefits! <hi>Salvation belongeth to the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſam 3.8.</note> 
                  <hi>and his bleſſing is upon his people. The King cryed to the Lord with his voyce,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 4.</note> 
                  <hi>and he heard him out of his holy Hill, and thou onely makeſt him</hi> and us <hi>to dwell in ſafety. Do thou, O Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſalm 4.8.</note> 
                  <hi>bleſſe the righteous, with favour do thou compaſs him as with a frieſt. O let the wickedneſs of the wicked come to an end,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>but eſtabliſh the juſt. Thou haſt maintained the Kings right and his cauſe, thou ſateſt in the Throne judging right.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou haſt been a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge for the oppreſſed, a Refuge in times of trouble, he that knows thy name will put his truſt in thee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 10. Pſalm 144.9.</note> 
                  <hi>for thou Lord haſt not forſaken him that ſought thee. And for this new mercy, will we ſing a new ſong to thee, yea, to thee will we ſing pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Thou alone giveſt ſalvation to Kings:</hi> Thou didſt deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Charles</hi> the ſecond, thy ſervant from the hurtfull ſword. Thou didſt preſerve him here at home all along thoſe ſharp Warres againſt his Royal Father; and when he was forced to flye into forraign parts for ſafety,
<note place="margin">Pſalm 11.1.</note> as a bird flees to the Mountaines, the wicked bending their bow, and making ready their arrow on the ſtring, thou haſt kept him ſafe in a ſtrange land. Bleſſed be thy holy Name, that when he was called home unto his Northern Kingdom, that neither the malice or filthy lucre of any evil perſons made a prey of him,
<note place="margin">Pſalm 21.3.</note> but that thou didſt prevent him with the bleſſings of goodneſſe; thou didſt ſet a Crown of pure Gold upon his head. And when his ſtraights forced him into his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Kingdom, thou didſt preſerve him in thoſe ſharp and dangerous encounters at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and when after that he
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:39205:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>was hunted as a Partridge in the Mountaines,
<note place="margin">Pſalm 27.5.</note> and was forced into the Woods and Wilderneſs; in the time of trouble thou didſt hide him in thy Pavillion, in the ſecret of thy Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle didſt thou hide him, and didſt ſet him up upon a Rock. And now is his head lifted up above his enemies round about him: therefore will we offer up in thy Tabernacles ſacrifices of joy. The Lord was the Kings ſtrength and his ſhield,
<note place="margin">Pſalm 28.</note> his heart truſted in him, and he is helped. Therefore his heart greatly rejoyceth, and with his ſong will he praiſe thee, the ſaving ſtrength of his anoynted. For thine anger endureth but a moment,
<note place="margin">Pſalm 30.</note> in thy favour is life, ſorrow hath endured for a night, but joy is now come in the morning, and thou haſt turned his mourning into dancing, thou haſt put off his ſackcloath, and girded him with gladneſs. Great were his dangers and ſtraits indeed,
<note place="margin">Pſalm 31. Pſalm 31.13.</note> but thou haſt not ſhut him up in the hand of the enemy, but haſt ſet his feet in a large room. We have heard the ſlander of many, fear was on every ſide whilſt they took counſel together againſt him, they deviſed to take away his life: But he truſted in the Lord, and ſaid, my times are in thy hand,
<note place="margin">Pſalm 55.18. Pſalm 64.1.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He hath delivered his ſoul in peace from the Battel that was againſt him: The Lord hid him from the ſecret Counſel of the wicked, and from the inſurrection of the workers of iniquity; Thou, O Lord, which didſt ſhew him great and ſore troubles,
<note place="margin">Pſalm 71.20.</note> haſt quickned him again, thou haſt increaſed his greatneſs and comſorted him on every ſide. Thou didſt ſeem indeed to caſt off, and to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor,
<note place="margin">Pſalm 89.38.</note> and to be wroth with thine anoynted; thou didſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane his Crown by caſting it to the ground: thou haſt broken down all his hedges, thou didſt bring his ſtrong Holds to ruine. But thou haſt given him the ſhield of thy ſalvation,
<note place="margin">Pſalm 18.35.</note> and thy right Hand hath holden him up, and thy gentleneſs hath made him great. Praiſed be God.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:39205:18"/>
            <head>AT THE THANKSGIVING. <hi>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NE</hi> 28. 1660.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 SAM. 19.15.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>So the King returned, and came to <hi>Jordan;</hi> and <hi>Judah</hi> came to <hi>Gilgal,</hi> to go to meet the King, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct the King over <hi>Jordan.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Very day indeed is, or ſhould be a Thanksgiving day. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.2.
<note place="margin">Mirum eſt quod Deum homo non ſemper laudat, cum omnis creatura ad Deum lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dandum ſemper cum invitat.</note> 
               <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day will I bleſs thee. Greg.</hi> ſaith, That it is ſtrange man ſhould not be almoſt alwayes prayſing God, when the Creatures are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes inviting him to praiſe God.</p>
            <p>Phyſicians obſerve, that a man hath as many parts or members in his body as there are dayes in the year, that no day ſhould paſs without prayſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:39205:19"/>to our Maker. But then we muſt diſtinguiſh, that every day is a day for Thanksgiving, but not a day of Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving. For if every day were a day of Thanksgiving, there could be no appointed ſelected dayes: of which ſelected dayes we have lately enjoyed one, and now God hath called us to another, and it is like the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, a good day, and a day of much gladneſs. Yea this day is even as that day, and much more abundant. For that day was kept upon the coming of the Kings Meſſage, this day upon the coming of the Kings perſon. That for an happy ſettlement hoped, this for an happy ſettlement begun. That for the bowing of the peoples hearts to his Majeſties return, this for the bowing the peoples knees to his Majeſties preſence. That laſtly for the Kings and people meeting by Letters and Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, this for their meeting in preſence and reality. That Thanksgiving was kept for the peoples invitation made to the King to return, this Thanksgiving is for the Kings return upon his invitation. So the King re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned and and came to <hi>Jordan,</hi> and <hi>Judah</hi> came to <hi>Gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Parts.</note> &amp;c,</p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">
                  <p>Or thus,</p>
                  <p n="1">1 King <hi>David</hi> his Regreſs, <hi>Returned</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. His progreſs, To <hi>Jordan.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. The peoples Egreſs, <hi>They went out to</hi> Gilgal.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs, which was their end, <hi>viz. To meet the King to conduct Him</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> Kings <hi>Davids</hi> return, ſo the King returned. 2. His Retirement, the ſtay thought fit to be made in the way for a little time, and came to <hi>Jordan, i. e.</hi> he ſtayed a little time on the other ſide <hi>Iordan.</hi> 3. The honour of his return, and <hi>Judah</hi> came to meet the King. 4. The ſafety of his Return, and <hi>Iudah</hi> came to meet him to conduct him over <hi>Iordan.</hi> 5. The place of <hi>Iudahs</hi> meeting, and that at <hi>Gilgal,</hi> a place of greateſt recept on this ſide <hi>Iordan,</hi> and neareſt to <hi>Iordan,</hi> the place ſo called from Gods rouling away the reproach of <hi>Egypt</hi> from <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> 1. Here firſt we learn the wiſdome and piety of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid.</hi> and what ſhould be in all good Princes, which is in an amicable and peaceable way to cloſe with their people ſubmitting to them, although they have gone aſtray for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly from their duty. Yea, though they had the power of revenge in their hand, and could probably even by
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:39205:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>dint of ſword cut their way home, <hi>David</hi> might, had he gone this way to work, have ſtayed from returning, till he knew he had power enough with him to overturn and overtop the ſtrength of <hi>Iudah,</hi> but, as he ſaith in the Pſalms, he was for peace, and that is a far better way, than the way of war, either for Prince or People. I think <hi>Cicero</hi> ſpake both truly and nobly, when he ſaid, <hi>Nihil hoc cive, nihil hoc homine tetrius, ſi aut civis aut home habendus eſt, qui bellum civile concupiſcit.</hi> Nothing is more fowl and hideous, than that inhabitant of a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or that man (if it be fitting to term him either an inhabitant or a man) that doth luſt &amp; wiſh for a civil war.
<note place="margin">Se malle unum ſervare civem, quam mille hoſtes occidere.</note> This was the good temper of <hi>Antonius Pius</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperour, who uſed to ſay as <hi>Scipio,</hi> he had rather ſave alive one true ſubject, than deſtroy a thouſand of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> choſe rather to return in peace, than return with war. When <hi>Neptune</hi> and <hi>Minerva</hi> both contend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about dignity, <hi>Neptune</hi> ſaid he invented water, a moſt uſefull Element: <hi>Minerva</hi> that ſhe invented the Olive, a moſt fruitfull tree, and the Emblem of fertili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and of peace, and ſhe carryed it from <hi>Neptune.</hi> There may be, I doubt not, many juſt cauſes of war in the world, but there is no greater calamity can be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined than a civil war: And I doubt whether there can be any juſt cauſe alledged of ſuch a broyl. The gates of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties were formerly the Courts of Juſtice, <hi>Geneſis</hi> 34.20. <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.24. <hi>Amos</hi> 5.10. <hi>Nicetas</hi> amongſt others, gives this reaſon, <hi>Vt civitatis populus eſſet pacificus, in quam diſcordes ingredi non liceret.</hi> And ſome think, that the cauſe why God would have the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites</hi> chooſe a King of their own native Countrey, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.15. and not a ſtranger, was, that there might be a more firm peace betwixt King and people upon their (if I may ſo term it) conſanguinity. It is witty, that of <hi>Lyranus,</hi> who gives the reaſon why <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.17. In <hi>Elim</hi> the people had by providence offered to them twelve
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:39205:20"/>wells of water;
<note place="margin">Dantur fontes ſecundum nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merum 12. trib. &amp;c. Mendoz.</note> and he ſayes, it was anſwerable to the twelve Tribes, <hi>&amp; ſic qualibet Tribus habuit fontem per ſe,</hi> every Tribe had his own well, that there might be no falling out, as if God had no leſs in his providence taken care to quench the fire of diſcord, than the heat of thirſt.
<note place="margin">Lib. 4. Antiqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cap.</note> That of <hi>Ioſephus</hi> alſo is not to be ſlighted, who gives this the cauſe why <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.16. God would have the people to gather every man an omer, and no more, becauſe if men had been left to gather as much as they would, the weakeſt would have wanted, and ſo there would have been ſome ſcuffling and diſcord about the <hi>Mannah.</hi> Our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24 7. gives this as a ſign of the worlds enſuing deſtruction, that kingdome ſhould riſe up againſt kingdom, and Nation againſt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and no doubt it is a ſign of a Nations deſtruction, when one party and power thereof ſhall riſe up againſt another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Applica.</hi> 1. Bleſſed be God therefore, and prayſed be his holy name, that our King is returned, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, <hi>i. e.</hi> without any more trouble or difference re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned in peace, yea, returned with peace, bringing with him affections of peace; yea, commands of peace.</p>
            <p>The dove is come back into the ark with the Olive branch of peace, but the ravenous vulture or raven, the bird of the prey, we hope is quite flown, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhall return again. We hope the waters are now well abated from off the face of the earth, and that the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing ſcourge of uſurpation and Tyranny is driven back, and oh that the Lord would be pleaſed to ſet the bow in the clouds, that he would give us ſome token for good that we ſhall be over-run no more. And to me there doth appear a very glorious rain-bow, which Chriſt the Sun of Righteouſneſs caſts by the beams of the holy Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, upon the following ſhowers of his own word, mens hearts every where being elevated beyond their ordinary pitch, and ſetting forth the <hi>Magnalia Dei</hi> beyond ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary expreſſion.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:39205:20"/> 2. Let us alſo make our return, let us return to our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Lawes, by obſerving them, to our former good cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes by uſing them; to our former obedience and all allegiance by continuing in them, but let us not return with the dog to the vomit, leſt as ſuch, we be turned out of the door of heaven, for without ſhall be dogs.</p>
            <p>We come now to King <hi>Davids</hi> retirement or ſtay by the way, and that was at <hi>Jordan;</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Part </seg>2</label> And perhaps that might be partly as hearing of the preparations that <hi>Iudah</hi> made to meet him and conduct him over <hi>Iordan;</hi> partly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure to ſtay for <hi>Amaſa's</hi> coming with his forces to guard him to his royal palace in <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Learn we hence,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſer. </seg>1</label> that it is the wiſdome of Princes to ſet themſelves in the way of their peoples love and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voire. It is no ambition or vain-glory in the leaſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in them to prepare themſelves to receive expreſſions of love, and duty, and gladneſs from their Subjects, then eſpecially when they ſee their people bent upon it, and their waving of it would ſeem rather a reſervation of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, or a purpoſe of revenge than a ſelf-denial. It is not to be ſuppoſed that <hi>David</hi> ſtayed on the other ſide, to ſee if <hi>Iordan</hi> would be driven back, and a way cut thorow the water for his paſſage: As for <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> no doubt <hi>David</hi> might have had a Convoy there to have conducted him over <hi>Iordan,</hi> but he lik'd much better to have a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy of his own native Subjects, whoſe faces no doubt he thirſted to ſee.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſer. </seg>2</label> That as King <hi>David</hi> was before hand with his Subjects in a meſſage of peace, for he ſends firſt, ſo is he before hand in his return in peace, for he comes firſt to <hi>Iordan,</hi> before <hi>Iudah</hi> comes to <hi>Gilgal.</hi> The motion of the King being like the <hi>Primum mobile,</hi> which being above the orbes, moves them with its motion. King <hi>David</hi> moves forward firſt towards the men of <hi>Iudah,</hi> and then the men of <hi>Iudah</hi> move forward toward King <hi>David.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That Nation is like to be a bleſt and happy Nation,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:39205:21"/>where the Prince and Princes are moſt forward to peace, and moſt forward to piety. <hi>Regis ad exemplum totus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponitur orbis,</hi> Pſ. 148. The Pſalmiſt makes a catholick motion to all the creatures to praiſe God. Well, but what creatures muſt lead the way? The high and moſt honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able creatures muſt firſt move: amongſt animate creatures he names angels, they are thrones and dignities, <hi>v.</hi> 2. praiſe him all ye angels, and what after? Men. And what men firſt? Princes firſt, and then all people, <hi>v.</hi> 11. Kings of the earth and all people. Thus is it in the other rank of creatures which are without life. Firſt ſun and moone, and then the middle region, <hi>v.</hi> 3. and 4. and then lower than that, the earth, and then lower than that, the deepes, <hi>v.</hi> 7. Indeed no houſe joyned ſo near to the temple as the Kings houſe, to ſhew that as they are neareſt God in dignity, they ſhould be neareſt God in ſanctity. Yea, to come nearer to our inſtance here, the firſt in offices of kindneſs and love. More ready to bleſſe then curſe. <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.12.13. what tribes were the bleſſing tribes? ſuch as deſcended from the free woman, the other from the ſervants moſtly,
<note place="margin">Mendoz</note> to ſhew that the work of bleſſng is moſt ſuitable to the moſt noble and ingenuous, and the work of curſing to the meaneſt. Ambroſe tells us, the maiſter Bee is larger then the reſt, but he never ſtings, ſo ready is true majeſty to clemency.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Application.</hi> There is no difficulty to draw this to our preſent occaſion. The Text and day falling in together al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in every part; We have a King in both, and here is a water betwixt the King and his people, the King in the Text ſtayd beyond the water for the conduct of <hi>Judah,</hi> and the King in the day ſtayed beyond the water for the conduct of his people in the navy, yea ſtayed for a time upon the water, till <hi>Amaſah</hi> and the reſt came to meet him; He ſets himſelf both inoffenſively and prudently, yea lovingly in the way of his
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:39205:21"/>peoples joyfull reception of him. As he was firſt in the meſſage, ſo was he firſt in the motion towards a meeting. Our buſineſſe and duty is to bleſſe God for the leaſt ſtirrings, and the very firſt procedures to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards an happy cloſing. It is ſome matter of joy to the mother, when the child begins but to ſtir in the womb, though the full rejoycing is not till the child be borne. Theſe day-breakes and dawnings of ſettlement were praiſe-worthy in the Kings coming to the ſea-ſide, expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a loyal and an honourable waftage over, in his ſetting forward to us; and bleſſed be God that our hopes were not ſtifled in the womb, but that there was a paſſage on forward; and to lay that forth, I muſt paſſe on in my Text to the third general part, <hi>the men of Judahs Egreſs, and Judah came to</hi> Cilgal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judah came to Gilgal:</hi> that is,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Part</hi> 3.</note> either the moſt of the people, or the beſt of the people which are before called the men of <hi>Judah;</hi> that is, the Nobility and Gentry of <hi>Judah</hi> with many of the chief Citizens of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and that nothing may be wanting to the remarkable fulneſs of the parallel, theſe were they that dwelt in the South-eaſt of <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> which was the ſeat of <hi>Judah,</hi> and the place of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the cheif <hi>Metropolis</hi> of the whole Land; happily there might be ſome out of other tribes or counties, but the maine body that appeared in the meeting of <hi>David,</hi> was of perſonages inhabiting the South-eaſt, at leaſt there were more South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtern men than of any one quarter. The very explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this ſaves me the labour of application afterwards; I hope there is but few ſo ignorant of the coaſts, as that I ſhould need to ſpread a map before them.</p>
            <p>Nay, yet more, I ſhall before I have done, finde out a <hi>Gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal</hi> in our South-eaſt borders; for that City in <hi>Jewry</hi> was ſo called of the Lord, becauſe he had there rowled away the reproach of <hi>Egypt, Joſh.</hi> 5.9. And that reproach of <hi>Egypt</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:39205:22"/>was twofold, one that they had been ſlaves there, and bondmen, and therefore it was called the houſe of bondage; the other, that they had not been circumciſed in the wilderneſs, and herein were become like to <hi>Egyptians</hi> uncircumciſed; now both theſe reproaches were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, the former by their coming into <hi>Canaan,</hi> the latter by being circumciſed, the former is implicitly laid down and to be under ſtood, the latter is expreſly ſet out to be read. And truly whereſoever it was neare the ſea-coaſts, that this late great appearance of Engliſh ſubjects met there leige Lord, it may well be called a <hi>Gilgal,</hi> as it puts us into poſſeſſion of one prevailedge, and puts us in hope of another correſponding to the two former.</p>
            <p>For firſt I hope, the reproach of our worſe than <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> ſlavery, is rowled a way, whoſe miſery was almoſt like <hi>Canaans</hi> curſe, a ſervant, of ſervants ſhall he be, we were ſubjects unto ſubjects, yea to very ſervants, that having got up, tyrannized to ſome purpoſe. Yea, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as for the ſakes of a few the land lay under the reproach of baſe diſloyalty and treachery to the King, I truſt that is rowled a way in this meeting; and as for the other, I hope every one will do their part that it may be done away, that we may not be lookt upon any longer as on an unbaptized nation in any part of it, which I look upon as a reproach to us.</p>
            <p>Now for obſervation, this coming of <hi>Judah</hi> to <hi>Gilgal,</hi> teaches us firſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>1</label> That when we have begun a work of righteouſneſs or piety, we ſhould go on forward with it. It was not enough for them to ſend a dutifull meſſage to their King to encourage him to a returne, but it was their duty to encourage him and aſſiſt him in his returne. It is one thing to ſay you may come if you pleaſe; an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other thing to promiſe him all honourable aſſiſtance at his coming, many begin well, but are quickly at a ſtan, d <hi>Gen.</hi> 28. The angells upon <hi>Jacobs</hi> ladder were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:39205:22"/>aſcending or deſcending, none ſtanding ſtill: <hi>Bern. ſic neceſſe eſt ſpiritum noſtrum aut proficere, aut deficere.</hi> Chriſt choſe to do good works on the Sabbath; to ſhew, that though we ſhould reſt from ſecular works on the Sabbath day, yet never ſhould reſt from doing good, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.8. <hi>Charity never failes:</hi> Duties likewiſe of humanity and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility ſhould never fail.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>2</label> That Subjects muſt be ready to ſhew all due regard, and to give all good encouragement to their injured and offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Princes. King <hi>David</hi> had been much injured and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked by a conſiderable party in <hi>Judah.</hi> They could not therefore in common civility or common pollicy do leſs than go to meet their King; nay doubtleſs, what they did was to expreſs their love and hearty alacrity in receiving home their exiled Prince. But of this afterwards.</p>
            <p>They choſe <hi>Gilgal</hi> as their generall rendezvouſe to put themſelves into a fit Poſture to meet the King.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>3</label> Teaching us, not only to chuſe fit times, but alſo fit places for all worthy actions or good enterprizes. The fitteſt places for Hearing, and the fitteſt for Praying, and the fitteſt for all civil actions. There is much choyce and wiſdome in all ſuch things. Circumſtances are very preſervative of, or very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to Subſtantials.</p>
            <p>We come now to the fourth part,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Part. </seg>4</label> which is the end of their egreſs to <hi>Gilgal,</hi> and that is <hi>congreſsus,</hi> to meet the King, and to teſtifie their readineſs and joyfulneſs in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of his royal Perſon.</p>
            <p>And indeed this was not only a very ſplendid, but an hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, and not only an happy, but a fruitfull meeting. And whileſt I unfold it, and put you into a window to behold it, carry along in your thoughts the meeting of our King and his ſubject, and ſuppoſe that what is ſaid of the one is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the other: And in this one meeting I ſee ſeven very happy meetings, and very handſome Congreſſes.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A meeting of ſtrength and Magnificence.</item>
               <item>2. Of ſafety and Honour.</item>
               <item>3. Of lawfull Government and true Subjection.</item>
               <item>4. Of Pardon and ſubmiſſion.</item>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:39205:23"/>
               <item>5. Of Mercy and Truth.</item>
               <item>6. Righteouſneſs and Peace.</item>
               <item>7. Rejoycing and Praiſing.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. Strength and Magnificence. You may imagine by what hath lately been at home, the ſtrength that was at <hi>Gilgal</hi> when <hi>Judah</hi> the ſtrongeſt Tribe was there; and ſure, if they be cloathed with ſoft Rayment that are in Kings Houſes, they would not offer to meet the King, as the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> did with old clouted ſhooes, or thred-bare patcht Coats; it is very probable there appeared at <hi>Gilgal</hi> the very bravery of <hi>Judah,</hi> therefore there was a meeting of ſtrength and magnificence: ſtrength in the multitude, and magnificence in the Attire and accoutrement.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Upon this, here is a meeting of ſafety and Honour. The King is ſafely received from the number and loyalty of his people, and he is honourably received from the number and quality of his people: ſo that as ſtrength and magnificence, ſo ſafety and honour waited upon him. And this we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to praiſe God for this day. For there was a time when he could not come for divers yeares into his own Kingdoms, but with danger to his life, and in fear to have his honour laid in the duſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.13. They took Counſel together againſt him, they deviſed to take away his life. But now (God be praiſed for it) he hath preſerved his life from fear of the enemy, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 64.1. God hath ſhewed him the path of life, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.11. He asked life of the Lord, and he gave it him, whileſt he preſerved his life in former yeares when dangers were round about him,
<note place="margin">Pſalm 18.4. verſe 5. Pſalm 21.5.</note> when the ſorrows of death compaſt him, and the floods of ungodly men made him affraid. In his diſtreſs he called on the Lord, and cryed unto his God, and he heard his voyce out of his Temple. His Glory is great in thy ſalvation (O Lord) Honour and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty haſt thou laid upon him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Meeting of lawfull Government and loyal ſubjection. <hi>Abſolom</hi> was no lawfull Governour, and <hi>Judah,</hi> when they ſet him up, or did acknowledge him, were no loyal ſubjects, for the alliegance they did owe was to <hi>David,</hi> not to <hi>Abſolom.</hi> For a people with activity, approbation and contrivance to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:39205:23"/>ſet up a falſe power, cuts the very ſinews of true Alliegiance, and ſuch poſſibly a conſiderable part of <hi>Judah</hi> had been. But now, here is an happy meeting of recovered true Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy and true Allegiance. What before was lawleſs, is now not only lawfull, but joyfull, not only warrantable, but ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry righteous. And God be bleſſed, that our eyes have lately ſeen ſuch a meeting, that true and faithfull ſubjects, and a true and lawfull Prince have met together.</p>
            <p>The fourth meeting, is of Pardon and ſubmiſſion. Both, though not expreſt, yet to be ſuppoſed, who can otherwiſe than imagine but that the people did humbly ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in this day of his power; and who can think other, but that the King who pardon'd <hi>Shim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i,</hi> and granted him his life for his own life, granted alſo a pardon to the men or <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> who had not done after the ſimilitude of <hi>Shi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>'s</hi> tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, who was pardoned for the time paſt for what he had done, not for what he ſhould after do, if he ſhould of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend again, and this only for his own life and Reigne. Nor was it againſt <hi>Davids</hi> oath made to <hi>Shimei,</hi> to give order to <hi>Solomon</hi> to put him to death: for no doubt <hi>David</hi> did know his diſpoſition and principles, as one likely on the like oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to be as impudent and inſulting as ever; nor did <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> order <hi>Solomon</hi> directly to put him to death for that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, for then <hi>Solomon</hi> had done it without any further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay, but <hi>Solomon</hi> did not, only confined him to the line, gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him a tether long enough. This leads me to the fifth meeting of Mercy and Truth which were here met together, that is, mercy and faithfulneſs.</p>
            <p>For, as Gods mercies to <hi>David</hi> were ſure, and therefore are called <hi>the ſure Mercies of</hi> David, and in that ſenſe Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Truth now met: ſo <hi>Davids</hi> mercies to his people and his enemies were ſure mercies, and ſo they met again.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Righteouſneſs and Peace met in this great meeting: for, as in Warrs civil, eſpecially all unrighteouſneſs, cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, outrages do prevail, ſo that we may ſay, war and unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs meet together, ſo Peace and Righteouſneſs meet together. For, <hi>inter arma non ſolum ſilent leges, ſed virtutes,</hi> but in peace, <hi>vigent leges, vigent virtutes:</hi> and we know that moral Vertues are concatenated, as <hi>Pindar</hi> in <hi>Olymp.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:39205:24"/>As there is not only peace but a League amongſt the Vertues, ſo this peace is confirmed by peace. Oh bleſſed is that meeting when King and people meet together in peace, eſpecially after a time of diſtance, and a time of broi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es.</p>
            <p>Therefore in the ſeventh and laſt place, there was in this meeting a congreſs of rejoycing and praiſing God; and this I conjecture, though I find it not written, by what our eyes have lately ſeen, in which there was as much joy and praiſing God by ſober and religious perſons, as ever was ſeen upon any occaſion. We read, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12.40. there was joy in <hi>Iſrael</hi> when <hi>David</hi> was inaugurated King, and why not when he was reſtored; There was occaſion, there was place for joy any bleſſing God. The end of this meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is our Text to conduct the King over <hi>Jordan:</hi> that is, to bring him with honour into his native Kingdom. No doubt, it was a welcome conduct to him to be brought in by them, whom he ſtyles his Brethren, his bones, and his fleſh. If he had had the conduct of all the valianteſt men and moſt honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable perſonages of all the Nations round about, it could not have pleaſed the ſoul of <hi>David</hi> ſo well, as to have the men of <hi>Judah</hi> to fetch him home.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſer. </seg>1</label> If a mans wayes pleaſe the Lord, he will make his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to be at peace with him, and not that only, but will teach both friends and enemies to ſerve and honour him, <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.27. He that diligently ſeeks good, procures favour, yea, and procures honour, and ſervice, and attendance, if God ſee it meet for him, <hi>Proverbs</hi> 14.28. In the multitude of people is the Kings honour, how much more when they ſhall meet together purpoſely in multitudes to preſent honour to him, <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.21. He that followeth after Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs and mercy, findeth Life, Righteouſneſs and Honour. <hi>David,</hi> no doubt, did ſet his heart to do works of remarkable righteouſneſs and remarkable mercy, and he finds life, God preſerves him in the midſt of moſt urgent and imminent dangers, when his life was hunted and ſought for, and when they laid ſnares privily, ſaying, who ſhall ſee us. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, He finds Righteouſneſs, which is <hi>Suum cui<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tribuere,</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:39205:24"/>he hath his Own given him again, of which he was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſly deprived. Thirdly, He finds honour, to have as much given him as poſſibly could be given at ſo ſhort warning. Righteouſneſs found, ſeems to be the ſuitable reward of Righteouſneſs done, and honour conferred, ſeems to be the reward of Alliance to mercy beſtowed; and life ſeems to be the common reward of both. He follows righteouſneſs, and finds life, and he follows mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and finds life, for life is defended by Juſtice, and ſaved by Mercy.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſer. </seg>2</label> How ready good ſubjects ſhould be to make a fitting compenſation to their Kings and Princes for their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries that have been offered to them. <hi>David</hi> was baſely and unworthily forced to fly out of the land, now there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they bring him back with honour. He was forced to ſlip away privately over <hi>Jordan;</hi> now they make for him an honourable conduct at his return. <hi>Nil <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am niſi vota ſuperſunt.</hi> My Application of the Premiſes ſhall be ſupplication with Thanksgiving.</p>
            <p>The Kings glory is great in thy ſalvation; (O Lord) Majeſty and Honour haſt thou laid upon him. Thou haſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him ſafety after danger, boldneſs after fear, joy after grief, gain after loſs, eſtabliſhment after exile, reſtitution after perſecution, honour after dejection, teſt after pertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, a Throne after a thorn, a Crown after a croſs. He fled away over this <hi>Jordan</hi> with little more than his ſtaff, and now he is become according to thy grant and his Right, the King in actual poſſeſsion of more than two great Kingdoms. What ſhall we render unto thee for what thou haſt done for him? Praiſe is comely, but it is too little; we can give nothing to thee, but what is thine own; but alas! what can ſuch poor beggars as we are give thee; Bleſſed Lord, thou giveſt us the grace to beg, that thou mayeſt give us the grace we do beg. Now for Jeſus his ſake, grant to our gracious King, increaſe of all Grace, perſeverance in all good, Wiſdome in all diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, Courage in all his noble enterprizes, Moderation in all proſperity, Patience in all adverſity, Succeſs in his
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:39205:25"/>undertakings, Honour in his atchievements, Joy in his Crown and dignity. Bleſs him (O Lord) with an obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient people, a learned, pious and painfull Clergy, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and loving Gentry, a loyal and gracious Nobility, a juſt and couragious Magiſtracy, a wiſe and faithfull Counſel. Bleſs the two royal Brethren, through thy Mercy here with us, and the two royal Siſters beyond the water. Let thy bleſsing reſt upon this honourable and happy Parliament, and upon thoſe wiſe Commanders and loyal Subjects that have been inſtrumental in this great work. Finally (O Lord) Bleſs his Majeſty with a long life, and an happy Reign; and when he muſt no longer reign over us, let him for ever reign with Chriſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <hi>Amen</hi> and <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:39205:25"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39205:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39205:26"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39205:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39205:27"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
